- My name is Nathan fielder,
and I graduated from one
of Canada's top business schools
with really good grades.
Now, I'm using my knowledge
to help struggling
small business owners make it
in this competitive world.
This...
Is Nathan for you.
Underneath this man's clothes
is a huge gift from god.
Can you guess what it is?
That's right.
His Santa claus body.
James Bailey has been
a professional Santa
for over 20 years.
And if you looked like him,
you'd be one too.
- I am 6'4",
and I do weigh 350 pounds.
- Holy [bleep].
- Yeah, holy [bleep].
- Yeah.
- I mean, my doctors would
like me to lose some weight.
- So it's the trade-off
between living longer
or dying and getting
to be Santa.
It's like, what's better?
It's hard to say.
- Well, it's very hard to say.
- But for someone so committed
to bringing us joy,
it's a shame that,
for most of the year,
James is completely out of work.
- In the summertime,
Santa claus
becomes a homeless person.
- But I wouldn't be here
if I didn't have a solution.
So you know
how the best time to buy
a winter coat is in the summer?
'Cause that's
when all the sales are.
- Yes.
- So what I'm thinking
is that same approach...
With Santa.
- I'm not seeing
how that applies to Santa claus.
- Every Christmas,
people line up in malls
to get their pictures taken
with Santa.
But what if you could do it
when it's less crowded
and at half the cost?
The plan:
Discount photos with Santa
in the summer.
- Yeah, that's a great idea.
- I can see the dollar signs
in your eyes.
- [Laughing]
- Yeah.
- Right.
- For this to work,
we needed to get
a shopping mall onboard,
and mall manager
sweeney montinola
at the southbay pavilion
in Carson, California,
was happy to let us
try out our concept.
- I think Santa in the summer
is a fun and unique idea,
and it will be great
for southbay pavilion.
- With a mall onboard,
it was now time to buy
the supplies
for our Christmas village.
Which stuff do you rent for
the most, which holiday?
- Christmas.
- Christmas?
- Yes.
- Okay.
You really shoved this away
in a corner, huh?
- Yep.
[Laughing]
- No one likes this?
- Yes.
- But after renting our props,
something bad happened.
The mall's policy
requires a background check
on all employees.
But when we had one run
on James,
something actually turned up.
So I paid him a visit
to see what the story was.
You have a criminal record?
- Well, yeah.
The only...
it was a misdemeanor,
really, from a dui
many years ago.
- Okay.
I couldn't believe
what I was hearing,
but then again,
from the first day I met James,
I could tell he was different
from other santas.
- This is a Smith & Wesson
.500 Magnum.
This is a .45 caliber
semi-automatic.
.22 rifle.
The ak-47.
This is a .300.
Little shotgun
in case you're into shotguns.
This is a .357 Magnum,
and that one is loaded.
- Okay, we can't take out
a loaded gun.
And there hasn't been
any other crimes
that I should know about.
- No, there's nothing there.
- Even though James
had a criminal record
and a closet full of guns,
I could still tell
he was a good guy.
But when I went back
to southbay pavilion,
they didn't see it that way.
- I wouldn't allow anyone
that has any kind of background
to be that close to kids.
- I mean,
he's a really good guy.
I think you'd really like him.
- No and no.
- Okay.
- Definitely no.
- I didn't know
how to tell James
that the mall didn't want him,
but I paid him a visit
to break the news.
- It's also important
if we could have it set up
so that we could print
the photos right there.
- Right.
- You know,
so we do the digital.
We get the pictures taken.
- Sure, sure.
- So that might help
draw more people in.
- Right, so I spoke
to the director of marketing
at the mall.
- Okay.
- And... uh...
- They're okay with us doing it?
Yeah?
Great.
So we're gonna
make this happen then.
That's outstanding.
[Laughter]
- Yeah.
- Good.
- I just gotta say thank you.
Really.
I think this is awesome.
- James seemed so excited,
and I just didn't have the heart
to tell him that he
wasn't wanted by the mall.
So my only goal
was to make it happen.
My hope was that,
if we got in there early,
we could do about 1/2 hour's
worth of photos with James
before anyone realized
we weren't supposed to be there.
So on the morning of August 2nd,
we quietly pulled our truck up
behind the jcpenney.
And before unloading
the village,
I had a quick word with James.
Just so you know,
if I ever say "abort,"
we should just walk
to the exit if you can.
- Abort.
- Yeah.
- Um...
Okay.
- Okay.
That's it.
All right, quicker, guys.
We're gonna be doing
a Santa display soon.
Maybe over here.
Maybe, like,
the background is here.
Do you want your picture taken
with Santa?
Come.
- Hi, there.
- Hey, yeah!
- What's your name?
- Here, come here, little one.
Yes.
You know how to do it.
Yeah.
Big smile.
Look at the camera.
- The mall manager.
What's her name again?
I'm, uh, nat...
I'm just an elf.
Wait.
Um...
would you like
your photo taken with Santa?
$5 only.
It's discounted prices
'cause it's earlier in the year.
- Excuse me.
- Okay, come.
Okay.
Let's go.
Come on.
- This way.
[Radio chatter]
Excuse me.
Hey, can you stay away
from the cameras, please?
You can't go in front of...
please.
Can you stay away
from our camera person?
Okay, we're going.
- That's nice.
- We are leaving.
- Nathan, you want me
to stop him?
I said, does he want me
to stop you?
Yeah.
[Cackling]
You've never messed
with Santa claus, have you?
- All right, okay.
- Just cool it, dude.
- No, it's okay.
James.
I'm out of the door.
Stop it.
- Oh, my goodness.
- James, come with me.
[We wish you a merry Christmas
playing]
♪
Okay, I know... we're both
trying to do our jobs.
Okay, don't swear.
There's kids around.
Do not swear.
- Now!
- There's kids around.
You can't swear
when there's children around.
Yes, I'm walking.
We're both trying to do
our jobs, okay?
So you can't think your job's
more important than mine.
- Well...
- watch out.
- Stay back, please.
You can't say the "f" word
around kids.
- What just happened?
- Okay, um...
[Sighs]
When I talked
to the mall manager
and I told her
about the criminal record thing,
she didn't wanna have us.
- [Sighs]
- So we weren't allowed...
To be in there.
- That came up?
- But I didn't wanna tell you
because I thought you'd be sad.
- [Grunts]
- So I wanted
to go through with it.
I mean, i... i honestly felt like
it's a human rights issue.
You have to be able
to be able to do this
when you did something
so small in the past.
- That guy almost wanted
to fight.
- But just what you did,
stepping up to him,
just again proves,
like, my point
of how great of a guy you are.
- [Laughing] Oh.
- And just how much
you deserve to be doing this.
- Well, yeah, this is great.
The little kids are enjoying it.
That was fun.
- The main point is
we made a stance.
- Okay.
- And we did what was right.
- All right.
- You understand?
- Yeah, I'm with you there.
- Merry Christmas, bro.
- Okay, guy.
[Laughing] All right.
- Okay.
- ♪ Noel, Noel
- It felt good to help someone
with a criminal record
redeem themselves.
But what if
I could prevent someone
from entering a life of crime
while they were still young?
When I see stuff like this,
I see what's probably a teenager
headed down the wrong path.
So I decided to catch a teen
doing graffiti
and then warn his parents before
he turns to a life of crime.
To do this, I created a series
of fake promotional posters
for my TV show
that may seem innocuous,
but to an immature vandal,
would be extremely tempting
to deface.
To see which one
would work best,
we left the posters up
for a week in several locations
around the city of Los Angeles.
To my surprise,
the "every penny counts" poster,
"risk equals reward,"
"tie shoes for safety,"
and "be flexible"
didn't attract any graffiti
at all.
However, "dream big"
and "stand up
to the big guys" did.
I decided to go
with "stand up to the big guys"
since there was opportunity
for two [bleep]s
and put it up on a wall
near a local high school.
I left a pen and added a sticker
that would make the act
even more irresistible
to an immature smart aleck.
With all the elements in place,
I watched from a Van
across the street,
ready to pounce at any moment.
We'll check back with this
in a bit.
But first...
Terry fox has been running
this petting zoo
in oak Glen, California
for years.
Can I touch the fat pig?
- Yes, you may.
Absolutely.
- But with several
other petting zoos
located closer to the major city
of Los Angeles,
Terry needs to give people
a good reason to visit hers.
And that's where I come in.
People don't go
to seaworld to see a whale.
They go to see shamu.
- Right.
- Who's your shamu?
- Our shamu is our petting farm.
Our pigs, our goats.
- Shamu is one animal.
- Right.
So if I had one animal to pick,
um, it would be the pigs.
- The pigs is multiple...
- Multiple, yes.
- Animals.
- Mm-hmm.
- So you don't...
- you just...
- you don't have a shamu.
- We just don't have one shamu.
No, we don't.
- My mission was to make
oak Glen petting zoo
a destination.
And what they needed
was a star animal.
The plan:
To create a hero pig
by staging a viral video
in which he rescues a baby goat
from drowning.
- Oh, okay.
- So I think
if you had a video like that,
people would come from places
as foreign as Japan,
and even more foreign
like China,
just to see your hero pig.
- That would be great.
- The first step
was picking our animals.
Vince would be our hero pig,
and gangster the goat
would be our victim.
The zoo had a large trout pond,
so this would be the setting
for our rescue.
But when I brought Vince
near the water,
I realized
he was an incredible coward.
[Vince squealing]
Okay, okay!
Okay, okay, okay!
- No, no, no, no!
- So we hired
some animal handlers
to bring in
a professional movie pig
that looked identical to Vince.
The question now was
how do we get a pig
to rescue a goat on camera?
Answer?
You can't.
So I decided to have
two scuba divers
secretly submerged
beneath the animals
guiding the pig towards the goat
to make it look
like a real rescue.
During
the first couple attempts,
the pig kept slipping
out of the divers' hands.
So we decided to build
an underwater track
out of pvc to guide the pig
like a bowling ball
going down a bumper Lane.
This worked a lot better,
and I was hopeful it would
fool the Internet audience
into believing
this video was real.
But as the amount of people
involved began to grow,
including animal trainers,
stuntmen,
and humane society reps,
I started to get worried.
After all, word couldn't get out
that this was fake
or it would be
a disastrous scandal
for oak Glen.
So I asked everyone on set to
sign non-disclosure agreements
stating that they swore
not to tell anyone
the rescue was fake
or else they would face
the death penalty.
Even though my lawyer said
the death penalty clause
was not enforceable,
I still wanted
to leave it in there
so people knew
how serious I was.
After several failed attempts,
we finally got
the rescue on tape.
[Goat crying]
We had our video.
And it was great.
But now we needed
a convincing backstory.
If this goes viral,
the press will wanna know...
who filmed this video?
I couldn't be me with
my background in television.
People would smell a hoax
from a mile away.
But there was one person
no one would ever suspect.
Santa claus.
- In order to distance myself
from the pig rescuing
goat video,
I got James to agree to say
that he was the one who shot it.
So for believability,
I needed to record audio
of James
to make it sound
like he was there
on the day it was filmed.
- Goat in the water!
Goat in the water!
- Yeah.
Goat in the water.
- Now, I needed to be sure
that Terry was with the program.
So when the media
comes a-knocking...
- Mm-hmm.
- Here's what you say.
- Okay.
- Verbatim.
- I sometimes take the animals
out to the pond.
That day, I left to go get
my lipstick from the office.
That's when the goat
must've slipped in.
I never saw the rescue.
However, a good samaritan
showed me the video.
I never got his name
or his gender.
Now repeat.
- Gimme a minute.
- I sometimes...
- I sometimes take the animals
out to the pond.
- Here, I did write it down
for you.
- Thank you.
- With Terry's script
to memorize,
the hero pig story
was becoming more concrete.
- "When the goat slipped in."
Okay.
- But then I realized
I had one more mouth to shut.
While we were filming
the rescue,
one of the scuba divers, Alex,
was telling me
some pretty personal stuff
about actors he's worked with
in the past.
- Jennifer Aniston, Ben stiller.
Ben's pretty bold.
He had to do some kinda
nude water stuff
over in Hawaii...
For along came Polly.
I did that movie with him.
- Alex was clearly a liability,
and I couldn't have him
spilling details about our video
on his next job.
So I asked him to meet me
at the pico subway station
to have a little reminder chat.
Thanks for meeting me here.
- What's up?
- How's it going?
- No worries. Good.
- Good.
Oh, you're a bit tense.
- So, uh...
well, you know...
- stand right here.
So how you been?
- Good.
- I just wanted to ask.
Do you remember that "pig
rescues goat" video we made?
- Yeah.
- You haven't been talking
to anyone about that
or anything, have you?
- You look like you're trying
to like threaten me.
- What?
- You look like you're...
- no, no!
Not at all!
You're shoulders were sore.
That's why I was doing that.
- Come on.
- Just 'cause I'd be very...
Very upset...
- Yeah.
- If you told someone about...
- could you...
- all right, all right.
Okay, yes, I'm sorry.
No, I'm sorry. Yes.
I shouldn't have done that.
Yeah, but please
don't tell anyone, okay?
Okay. Thank you.
- No worries.
- Okay.
My paranoia
was getting the best of me.
The video hadn't even
been uploaded,
and I was already
getting worried
about people revealing
the secret.
Plus, watching the video again,
I started to doubt
that this would fool anyone.
- Goat in the water!
- All I could do at this point
was upload the video
and let the public decide.
- Goat in the water!
- When I woke up
the next morning,
I was astounded to see
that the video had been posted
on gawker, ebaumsworld,
and a bodybuilding
message board.
It had over 3,000 views,
and that was way more
than I ever expected.
Then I saw it was climbing
the charts on Reddit.
Then I checked the view count
an hour later.
Holy [bleep].
- By the way, this may sound
like a sea rescue,
but a goat...
a baby goat...
gets stuck in water.
- This is some pig.
You have to see it.
A goat at a petting zoo
got stuck in a lake.
- This really happened.
- That was cool!
- Have no fear,
there's a pig there.
I mean, you couldn't do this
at Warner brothers
as a cartoon
and make it seem more realistic.
- We're wayward duty-bound
to pass this on.
It's the leading
web video today.
While we have no way of knowing
if it's real,
this was apparently shot
at a petting zoo.
- Goat in the water!
- That's a baby goat
who got out into too deep water.
Begins crying for help.
Enter this pig.
- [Speaking native language]
- [Singing]
- It seemed like the whole world
was talking about my video.
For a moment, I felt bad
because it wasn't real.
But then I realized
that that didn't matter.
- Interspecies,
he went and helped...
learn from it, humans.
- In these cynical times,
people are desperate
for something to believe in.
And I gave people a reminder
that it's okay just to believe.
- How did the pig free the goat?
- Just kinda guided it,
just pushed him.
[Laughter]
- Every day with Elizabeth
is like "how did this happen?"
- I always knew this video
was something special.
And that's why, in the end,
I decided not to put the name
of the petting zoo on it.
I didn't want it
to come across like an ad,
you know, for the petting zoo.
- Mm-hmm, right.
- I thought it would be
a bit transparent.
- But if people would've known
that it was oak tree village...
- but I mean,
you can't be so selfish.
- Selfish?
- Well, I mean,
if people love the video,
it's like...
can't just be
all about the business.
- But that's what it was
supposed to be about
when you first came up.
It was supposed to be
about the business.
- Terry just didn't seem
to understand.
But I don't leave those
that I help empty-handed.
That's why I made her this sign.
- As my stakeout
for a young vandal continued,
I was starting
to get frustrated.
I'd been monitoring
the poster for over four hours,
and no one had defaced it.
For a moment, I thought
this wasn't going to work.
But I was quickly proven wrong.
Oh, he's taking the pen.
Oh, my god.
He's actually doing it.
On camera.
Let's go!
Hey, man.
- Hey.
- Hey, how's it going?
- It's going.
- Cool,
what are you doing there?
Oh, that's so funny.
You drew a [bleep].
- Yeah.
- Yeah, that's really funny.
We're doing a show
about teens... cool teens...
called "teen street."
- Uh-huh.
- Is it cool if we ask you
a few questions for the show?
- Sure, no problem.
- All right, cool.
That's really funny.
That's mega funny.
This teen was no good,
and his parents needed to know
what he did.
So to earn his trust,
I told him we wanted to make
an entire "teen street" episode
about him.
So we spent the rest
of his afternoon
shooting segments
for a fake show.
[Beeping]
- What up!
I'm Kyle.
19 years old.
And this is "teen street."
If you don't like it,
[Bleep] You.
[Laughing] I do whatever
the [bleep] I want,
and I can do whatever I want.
The thing I'm most proud of
is I make [bleep]load of money.
No regrets.
[Cheers and applause sounds]
- Listen to that!
- Bam.
Yeah, I skated for six years,
played the drums for six years,
and did muay tai
and Brazilian jiu jitsu.
You have to love your mom.
If you don't,
go [bleep] yourself.
- This show is about
the coolest teens in town.
Both: "Teen street," bitches!
- First tattoo when I was 13.
This is the only girl
that never complains to me.
[Moaning]
[Laughing]
All right, so now I'm gonna
show you where I live.
Let's do this.
- For the final part
of the segment,
I said we had to do a tour
of his house.
He didn't know it,
but he was leading me
right to his parents,
and I was going to tell them
what he did to my poster.
- What up?
This is my pad.
This is where I spend my time
making trouble.
I'm gonna show you a tour
real quick.
- So who's this lovely lady?
- This is my mom sheri.
- Awesome, man.
- Nice to meet you.
- Guess teens have moms.
- Right?
- Yeah.
All right, but we need
to stop laughing for a moment,
because we have to sit down.
I have something to talk about.
- Okay.
- He's drawn two penises
right there.
And you can see I'm holding them
as if I'm masturbating
these two men.
- [Laughs]
- Your s... you're laughing.
- I don't...
- what do you find...
is that funny to you?
- I... no.
This is not funny.
- The penises?
Do you like that?
- No.
- Being held like that?
[Laughter]
Is that...
so this is... okay.
So this is funny to you.
To my surprise, even his mom
wasn't taking this seriously.
Luckily, I had an LAPD officer
with me to set him straight.
What we have here is a crime.
If someone sees you
commit the crime,
you can get arrested
and go to jail.
And believe me,
you don't wanna go to jail.
- Would drawing penises
going into someone's hand
be a segue to, you know, murder?
- Of course not.
I don't think so.
- Never?
- I'm not gonna say never.
- So may... yes.
So then yes.
- If he choked on it, maybe.
- Kyle.
Show respect and apologize.
- It's a good way to go.
- All right, well,
I did enjoy drawing penises
next to your face,
but I really do apologize.
- No, I don't accept that.
I don't accept an apology
that starts like that.
- [Clears throat]
I apologize for drawing
a penis next to your face.
- Okay.
- All right.
- You're a good kid.
You have a lot of potential.
And to be honest,
I see some of myself in you.
But you just have to try
to become more like me
and less like you.
- No, I disagree.
I think he should more
like himself...
- well, he shouldn't be
like himself obviously.
Someone who draws penises.
[Overlapping comments]
[Engine sound passing by]
- It's always amazing to see
animals helping each other out.
- That guy said...
didn't he say something like,
"goat in the water!
Goat in the water!"
- Yeah.
- Or something like that.
And the pig jumped in.
- He's definitely on a mission.
He's definitely going
to save the goat.
Like, there's no way you can
say that he's not.
I love this video.